<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1123 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1123.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3542 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3542.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5452 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5452.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5681 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5681.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6891 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6891.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.dnsop-cookies SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-dnsop-cookies-04.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.dnsop-respsize SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-dnsop-respsize-15.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-dnsop-dns-message-fragments-00" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title>DNS message fragments</title>

    <author fullname="Mukund Sivaraman" initials="M." surname="Sivaraman">
      <organization>Internet Systems Consortium</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>950 Charter Street</street>
          <city>Redwood City</city>
          <code>94063</code>
          <region>CA</region>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>muks@isc.org</email>
        <uri>http://www.isc.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Shane Kerr" initials="S." surname="Kerr">
      <organization>Beijing Internet Institute</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2/F, Building 5, No.58 Jinghai Road, BDA</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100176</code>
          <country>CN</country>
        </postal>
        <email>shane@biigroup.cn</email>
        <uri>http://www.biigroup.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>


    <author fullname="Linjian Song" initials="L." surname="Song">
      <organization>Beijing Internet Institute</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2/F, Building 5, No.58 Jinghai Road, BDA</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100176</code>
          <country>CN</country>
        </postal>
        <email>songlinjian@gmail.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.biigroup.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Internet Area</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- <keyword>dns</keyword> -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a method to transmit DNS messages over
      multiple UDP datagrams by fragmenting them at the application
      layer. The objective is to allow authoriative servers to
      successfully reply to DNS queries via UDP using multiple smaller
      datagrams, when larger datagrams don't pass through the network
      successfully.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <section title="Background">
	<t><xref target="RFC1035" /> describes how DNS messages are to
	be transmitted over UDP. A DNS query message is transmitted
	using one UDP datagram from client to server, and a
	corresponding DNS reply message is transmitted using one UDP
	datagram from server to client.</t>

	<t>The upper limit on the size of a DNS message that can be
	transmitted thus depends on the maximum size of the UDP datagram
	that can be transmitted successfully from the sender to the
	receiver. Typically any size limit only matters for DNS replies,
	as DNS queries are usually small.</t>

	<t>As a UDP datagram is transmitted in a single IP PDU, in
	theory the size of a UDP datagram (including various lower
	internet layer headers) can be as large as 64 KiB. But
	practically, if the datagram size exceeds the path MTU, then the
	datagram will either be fragmented at the IP layer, or worse
	dropped, by a forwarder. In the case of IPv6, DNS packets are
	fragmented by the sender only. If a packet's size exceeds the
	path MTU, a Packet Too Big (PTB) ICMP message will be received
	by sender without any clue to the sender to reply again with a
	smaller sized message, due to the stateless feature of
	DNS. In addition, IP-level fragmentation caused by large DNS
	response packet will introduce risk of cache poisoning
	<xref target="Fragment-Poisonous"/>, in which the attacker can
	circumvent some defense mechanisms (like port, IP, and query
	randomization <xref target="RFC5452"/>).
	</t>

	<t>As a result, a practical DNS payload size limitation is
	necessary.  <xref target="RFC1035" /> limited DNS message UDP
	datagram lengths to a maximum of 512 bytes. Although EDNS(0)
	<xref target="RFC6891" /> allows an initiator to advertise the
	capability of receiving lager packets (up to 4096 bytes), it
	leads to fragmentation because practically most packets are
	limited to 1500 byte size due to host Ethernet interfaces, or
	1280 byte size due to minimum IPv6 MTU in the IPv6 stack <xref
	target="RFC3542" />. </t>

	<t>According to DNS specifications <xref target="RFC1035" />, if
	the DNS response message can not fit within the packet's size
	limit, the response is truncated and the initiator will have to
	use TCP as a fallback to re-query to receive large
	response. However, not to mention the high setup cost introduced
	by TCP due to additional roundtrips, some firewalls and middle
	boxes even block TCP/53 which cause no responses to be received
	as well. It becomes a significant issue when the DNS response
	size inevitably increases with DNSSEC deployment.</t>

	<t>In this memo, DNS message fragmentation attempts to work
	around middle box misbehavior by splitting a single DNS message
	across multiple UDP datagrams. Note that to avoid DNS
	amplification and reflection attacks, DNS cookies <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-cookies"/> is a mandatory requirement
	when using DNS message fragments.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Motivation">
	<t>It is not a new topic regarding large DNS packets(>512B)
	issue <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-respsize"/>, starting from
	introduction of IPv6, EDNS(0) <xref target="SAC016"/>, and
	DNSSEC deployment <xref target="SAC035"/>.  In current
	production networks, using DNSSEC with longer DNSKEYs (ZSK>1024B
	and KSK>2048B) will result in response packets no smaller than
	1500B <xref target="T-DNS"/>.  Especially during the KSK
	rollover process, responses to the query of DNSKEY RRset will be
	enlarged as they contain both the new and old KSK.</t>

	<t>When possible, we should avoid dropped packets as this means
	the client must wait for a timeout, which incurs a high
	cost. For example, a validator behind a firewall suffers waiting
	till the timeout with no response, if the firewall drops large
	EDNS(0) packets and IP fragments. It may even cause disaster
	when the validator can not recieve response for new trust anchor
	KSK due to the extreme case of bad middle boxes which also drop
	TCP/53.</t>

	<t>Since UDP requires fewer packets on the wire and less state
	on servers than TCP, in this memo we propose continuing to use
	UDP for transmission but fragment the larger DNS packets into
	smaller DNS packets at the application layer. We would like the
	fragments to easily go through middle boxes and avoid falling
	back to TCP.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="DNS Message Fragmentation Method">
      <section title="Client Behavior">
	<t>Clients supporting DNS message fragmentation add an EDNS
	option to their queries, which declares their support for this
	feature.</t>

	<t>If a DNS reply is received that has been fragmented, it will
	consist of multiple DNS message fragments (each transmitted in a
	respective UDP packet), and every fragment contain an EDNS
	option which says how many total fragments there are, and the
	identifier of the fragment that the current packet
	represents. The client collects all of the fragments and uses
	them to reconstruct the full DNS message. Clients MUST maintain
	a timeout when waiting for the fragments to arrive.</t>

	<t>Clients that support DNS message fragments MUST be able to
	reassemble fragments into a DNS message of any size, up to the
	maximum of 64KiB.</t>

	<t>The client MAY save information about what sizes of packets
	have been received from a given server. If saved, this
	information MUST have a limited duration.</t>

	<t>Any DNSSEC validation is performed on the reassembled DNS
	message.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Server Behavior">
        <t>Servers supporting DNS message fragmentation will look for
        the EDNS option which declares client support for the
        feature. If not present, the server MUST NOT use DNS message
        fragmentation. The server MUST check that DNS cookies are
        supported. [**FIXME**] Implementation of the first request case,
        where no existing established cookie is available needs
        discussion; we want to avoid additional round-trips here.
	Shane: don't cookies already handle this case?</t>

	<t>The server prepares the response DNS message normally. If the
	message exceeds the maximum UDP payload size specified by the
	client, then it should fragment the message into multiple UDP
	datagrams.</t>

	<t>Each fragment contains an identical DNS header with TC=1,
	possibly varying only in the section counts. Setting the TC
	flag in this way insures that clients which do not support DNS
	fragments can fallback to TCP transparently.</t>
	
	<t>As many RR are included in each fragment as are possible
	without going over the desired size of the fragment. An EDNS
	option is added to every fragment, that includes both the
	fragment identifier and the total number of fragments.</t>

	<t>The server needs to know how many total fragments there
	are to insert into each fragment. A simple approach would be
	to generate all fragments, and then count the total number at
	the end, and update the previously-generated fragments with
	the total number of fragments. Other techniques may be
	possible.</t>

	<t>The server MUST limit the number of fragments that it uses in
	a reply. [**FIXME**] Why? We should explain risk of congestion,
	packet loss, etc. We should also set upper limits.</t>

	<t>[**FIXME**] The following needs further discussion about the
	sizes; also an upper limit for each *fragment* has to be the
	client's UDP payload size as it is the driver and it alone knows
	the ultimate success/failure of message delivery. So if it sets
	a maximum payload size of 1200, there's no point in trying
	1460. Clients that support DNS message fragments (and signal
	support using the EDNS option) should adapt their UDP payload
	size discovery algorithm to work with this feature, as the
	following splits on sizes will assist PMTU discovery.</t>

	<texttable>
	  <preamble>The server should use the following sizes for each
	  fragment in the sequence in IPv4:</preamble>
	  <ttcol>Fragment ID</ttcol>
	  <ttcol>Size</ttcol>
	  <c>1</c><c>min(512, client_specified_max)</c>
	  <c>2</c><c>min(1460, client_specified_max)</c>
	  <c>3</c><c>min(1480, client_specified_max)</c>
	  <c>N</c><c>min(1480, client_specified_max)</c>
	  <postamble>The rationale is that the first packet will always get
	  through, since if a 512 octet packet doesn't work, DNS cannot
	  function. We then increase to sizes that are likely to
	  get through. 1460 is the 1500 octet Ethernet packet size,
	  minus the IP header overhead and enough space to support
	  tunneled traffic. 1480 is the 1500 octet Ethernet packet
	  size, minus the IP header overhead. [**FIXME**] Why not add 1240 here?
	  </postamble>
	</texttable>

	<texttable>
	  <preamble>The server should use the following sizes for each
	  packet in the sequence in IPv6:</preamble>
	  <ttcol>Fragment ID</ttcol>
	  <ttcol>Size</ttcol>
	  <c>1</c><c>min(1240, client_specified_max)</c>
	  <c>2</c><c>min(1420, client_specified_max)</c>
	  <c>3</c><c>min(1460, client_specified_max)</c>
	  <c>N</c><c>min(1460, client_specified_max)</c>
	  <postamble>Like with IPv4, the idea is that the first packet
	  will always get through. In this case we use the
	  IPv6-mandated 1280 octets, minus the IP header overhead.
	  We then increase to 1420, which is the 1500 octet Ethernet
	  packet size, minus the IP header overhead and enough space
	  to support tunneled traffic. 1460 is the 1500 octet Ethernet
	  packet size, minus the IP header overhead.
	  </postamble>
	</texttable>
      </section>
      <section title="Other Notes"><t>
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>The FRAGMENT option MUST NOT be present in DNS query
	  messages, i.e., when QR=0. If a DNS implementation notices the
	  FRAGMENT option in a DNS query message, it MUST ignore it.</t>

	  <t>In DNS reply messages, the FRAGMENT option MUST NOT be
	  present in datagrams when truncation is not done, i.e., when
	  TC=0. If a DNS implementation notices the FRAGMENT option in a
	  DNS reply message fragment datagram that is not truncated,
	  i.e, when TC=0, it MUST drop all DNS reply message fragment
	  datagrams received so far (awaiting assembly) for that
	  message's corresponding question tuple (server IP, port,
	  message ID) without using any data from them. [**FIXME**]
	  Dropping fragments to be received yet will be problematic for
	  implementations, but dropping fragments received so far ought
	  to be sufficient.</t>

          <t>[**FIXME**] Shane: why are we setting TC? Mukund: This is
          so that existing implementations that don't know about DNS
          fragments will look at TC=1, ignore any unknown options, and
          move to TCP. They will also drop additional fragments with the
          same DNS message identifier (the 16-bit one, not the fragment
          identifier).</t>

	  <t>More than one FRAGMENT option MUST NOT be present in a DNS
	  reply message fragment datagram. If a DNS implementation
	  notices multiple FRAGMENT options in a DNS reply message
	  fragment datagram, it MUST drop all reply datagrams received
	  for that message's corresponding question tuple (server IP,
	  port, message ID) without using any data from them. [**FIXME**]
	  Dropping fragments to be received yet will be problematic for
	  implementations, but dropping fragments received so far ought
	  to be sufficient.</t>

	  <t>[**FIXME**] What about TSIG?</t>
	</list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The ALLOW-FRAGMENTS EDNS(0) Option">

      <t>ALLOW-FRAGMENTS is an EDNS(0) <xref target="RFC6891" /> option
      that a client uses to inform a server that it supports fragmented
      responses. [**FIXME**] Why not simply use the FRAGMENT option here
      with count=0, identifier=ignored and avoid using another option
      code?</t>

      <section title="Wire Format">
	<t>TBD.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Option Fields">
	<section title="Maximum Fragment Size">
	  <t>The Maximum Fragment Size field is represented as an
	  unsigned 16-bit integer. This is the maximum size used by any
	  given fragment the server returns. [**FIXME**] This field's
	  purpose has to be explained.</t>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section title="Presentation Format">
	<t>As with other EDNS(0) options, the ALLOW-FRAGMENTS option
	does not have a presentation format.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The FRAGMENT EDNS(0) Option">

      <t>FRAGMENT is an EDNS(0) <xref target="RFC6891" /> option that
      assists a client in gathering the various fragments of a DNS
      message from multiple UDP datagrams. It is described in a
      previous section. Here, its syntax is provided.</t>

      <section title="Wire Format">
	<t>TBD.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Option Fields">
	<section title="Fragment Identifier">
	  <t>The Fragment Identifier field is represented as an unsigned
	  8-bit integer. The first fragment is identified as 1. Values
	  in the range [1,255] can be used to identify the various
	  fragments. Value 0 is used for signalling purposes.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Fragment Count">
	  <t>The Fragment Count field is represented as an unsigned
	  8-bit integer. It contains the number of fragments in the
	  range [1,255] that make up the DNS message. Value 0 is used
	  for signalling purposes.</t>
	</section>
      </section>
      <section title="Presentation Format">
	<t>As with other EDNS(0) options, the FRAGMENT option does not
	have a presentation format.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Considerations">
      <section title="Background">
	<t>TCP-based application protocols co-exist well with competing
	traffic flows in the internet due to congestion control methods
	such as in <xref target="RFC5681" /> that are present in TCP
	implementations.</t>

	<t>UDP-based application protocols have no restrictions in lower
	layers to stop them from flooding datagrams into a network and
	causing congestion. So applications that use UDP have to check
	themselves from causing congestion so that their traffic is not
	disruptive.</t>

	<t>In the case of <xref target="RFC1035" />, only one reply UDP
	datagram was sent per request UDP datagram, and so the lock-step
	flow control automatically ensured that UDP DNS traffic didn't
	lead to congestion. When DNS clients didn't hear back from the
	server, and had to retransmit the question, they typically paced
	themselves by using methods such as a retransmission timer based
	on a smoothed round-trip time between client and server.</t>

	<t>Due to the message fragmentation described in this document,
	when a DNS query causes multiple DNS reply datagrams to be sent
	back to the client, there is a risk that without effective
	control of flow, DNS traffic could cause problems to competing
	flows along the network path.</t>

	<t>Because UDP does not guarantee delivery of datagrams, there
	is a possibility that one or more fragments of a DNS message
	will be lost during transfer. This is especially a problem on
	some wireless networks where a rate of datagrams can continually
	be lost due to interference and other environmental
	factors. With larger numbers of message fragments, the
	probability of fragment loss increases.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Implementation Requirements">
	<t>TBD.</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Open Issues and Discussion">
        <t><list style="numbers">
	    <t>Resolver behavior
	    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
	    We need some more discussion of resolver behavior in
	    general, at least to the point of making things clear to
	    an implementor.
	    </t>
    	    <t>The use of DNS fragments mechanism
	    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
	    Is this mechanism designed for all DNS transactions, or
	    only used in some event or special cases like a key
	    rollover process? If the mechanism is designed for general
	    DNS transactions, when is it triggered and how is it
	    integrated with existing patterns?
	    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
	    One option is that DNS fragments mechanism works as a
	    backup with EDNS, and triggered only when a larger packet
	    fails in the middle. It will be orthogonal with TCP which
	    provide additional context that TC bit will be used in
	    server side.
	    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
	    </t>
	    <t>What is the size of fragments?
	    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
	    Generally speaking the number of fragment increases if
	    fragment size is small (512 bytes, or other empirical
	    value), which makes the mechanism less efficient. If the
	    size can changed dynamically according to negotiation or
	    some detection, it will introduce more cost and round trip
	    time.
	    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
	    </t>
	</list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>To avoid DNS amplification or reflection attacks, DNS cookies
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-cookies"/> must be used. The DNS
      cookie EDNS option is identical in all fragments that make up a
      DNS message. The duplication of the same cookie values in all
      fragments that make up the message is not expected to introduce a
      security weakness in the case of off-path attacks.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The ALLOW-FRAGMENTS and FRAGMENT EDNS(0) options require
      option codes to be assigned for them.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Stephen Morris, JINMEI Tatuya, Paul Vixie, Mark
      Andrews, and David Dragon for reviewing a pre-draft proposal and
      providing support, comments and suggestions.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="References">
      &RFC1035;&RFC1123; &RFC5681; &RFC6891;&RFC3542;&RFC5452;
      &I-D.dnsop-cookies;&I-D.dnsop-respsize;

    <reference anchor="Fragment-Poisonous">
	            <front>
	                <title>Fragmentation Considered Poisonous</title>
			<author fullname="Herzberg, A."  initials="A." surname="Herzberg"></author>
			<author fullname=" H. Shulman"  initials="H." surname="Shulman"></author>
			<date year="2012" />
	            </front>
	   </reference>
	   <reference anchor="SAC016">
            <front>
                <title>Testing Firewalls for IPv6 and EDNS0 Support</title>
                <author>
                    <organization>ICANN Security and Stability Advisory Committee</organization>
                </author>
                <date year="2007" />
            </front>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="T-DNS" target="http://www.isi.edu/~johnh/PAPERS/Zhu14b.pdf">
	        <front>
	                <title>T-DNS: Connection-Oriented DNS to Improve Privacy and Security (extended)</title>
			<author fullname="Liang Zhu"  initials="L" surname="Zhu"></author>
			<author fullname="Zi Hu"  initials="Z" surname="Hu"></author>
			<author fullname="J. Heidemann"  initials="J." surname="Heidemann"></author>
			<date year="2007" />
		</front>
	</reference>
		   <reference anchor="SAC035">
            <front>
                <title>DNSSEC Impact on Broadband Routers and Firewalls </title>
                <author>
                    <organization>ICANN Security and Stability Advisory Committee</organization>
                </author>
                <date year="2008" />
            </front>
     </reference>
     </references>

    <section title="Change History (to be removed before publication)">
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">

          <t>
	  draft-dnsop-dns-message-fragments-00
          <vspace/>
          Initial draft.
          </t>

        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
